Jag njuter verkligen av att göra saker
men jag började bli riktigt trött på att utföra andras idéer
och jag blev väldigt cynisk gentemot reklamvärlden
En stor del av arbetet vi gjorde var
att göra TV reklam
för att försöka sälja produkter jag inte är särkilt förtjust i
Så när jag var 29 sökte jag till
the Royal College of Art
för att gå en kurs som hette Design Products.
Ron Arad, arkitekten och formgivaren hade precis tagit över
proffesuren för den kursen
Jag blev erbjuden en plats och jag började där
och det introducerade mig för,
antar jag, den sortens arbete vi fortfarande gör, till denna dag:
kritisk design,
användande design för att ifrågasätta teknologi,
byggande en massa intressanta produkter som
skulle göra det istället för att använda det skrivna ordet,
nyttjande föremål och formgivna föremål för att
ändra hur vi tänker kring saker,
för att uppmuntra annorlunda tänkande kring
teknologi och teknologiska produkter.
Du har en enhet där signalen kommer in
men sen sänder den till dig
en låg frekvens in i munnen
och denna översätts till
en vibration
in i innerörat och den uppfattas som
ljud som strömmar, ett strömmande ljud.
Möjligheterna är oändliga,
en premiärminister kan ta emot hemlig vägledning från speciella rådgivare,
fotbollstränare kan förmedla taktiskta instruktioner till sina spelare
och ingen kommer någonsin att veta detta.
Föreställ dig en kille på aktiemarknaden,
om han är på teater, om han är på bio, om han ligger i sängen och sover, om han är på stranden
rykten från börsen om företag som kraschar och så
kan nå honom omedelbart och han kan reagera på detta.
Jag har börjat tänka på Mo's projekt om energioberoende
och jag har börjat titta på Madeiras landskap.
Det går inte att se så mycket av det på grund av hur kameralinsen är riktad
men åt det hållet jag tittar kan jag se dessa enorma bergssidor,
Madeira är extremt vertikalt.
Så jag började fundera på vad Mo's projekt kunde vara i Maderia.
och fick snabbt den här idén om gravitationsbatteriet.
Så huvudsakligen, i ett nötskal, är gravitationsbatteriet
en enhet som fungerar som ett lagringsmedium
så att du fortfarande kan använda solceller och vindturbiner,
vilket förnybar energigenerande teknik som helst, men denna energi
genereras om solen skiner, ofta när människor arbetar och inte är hemma,
när de inte behöver elförsörjning.
Den enda lösningen på detta för närvarande är att sälja tillbaka energin till nätet,
alltså till ägarna av infrastrukturen,
och år efter år har de sänkt priset som de köper tillbaka energi för, vilket gör det hela ogenomförbart.
Med gravitationsbatteriet gör vi det möjligt för människor att använda solenergi till att lyfta en massa
upp i luften, och med den stora mängden av bergssidor som finns i samhällen på Madeira kan det vara
allt mellan 10-14, hela vägen upp till 500 meter av vertikalitet.
Så ju större höjd du har, desto mer tid har du att släppa massan och därigenom kan du lagra mer energi.
Du lyfter massan under dagtid och när du kommer hem från arbetet behöver du energi,
det är mörkt, solen har gått ner och du kan släppa massan som faller genom rymden,
via en växellåda, vrider en generator som genererar elektricitet.
Allt är öppen källkod,
så vi tar bort aktörer som stora företag och tillverkningsindustri,
vi skapar något som är lätt att bygga, den nuvarande versionen använder en motorcykelmotor
som vi hittade på en lokal bilskrot, den är mycket billig,
så vi använder motorcykelns växellåda
eftersom den är mycket precis och redan byggd
och sen testar och leker vi lite med utväxlingen och med massan,
experimenterar med fallhastigheten och vi kan anpassa det till många olika hushållsprodukter.
I Nimes har vi myntat uttrycket "beboelighet" hos en värld.
Vi kan säga att design kan försöka
bibehålla eller förstärka
världens "beboelighet" för sina invånare, män och kvinnor.
Vi tolkar verbet "bebo" på flera nivåer.
Den primära nivån är uppenbarligen materiell,
och innebär att bebo en rymd, skyddad från väderförhållanden etc. Jag kommer inte att uppehålla mig vid denna nivå.
Sen har vi beboelighet från ett livsnödvändigt perspektiv,
där vi behöver behålla hälsan,
på ett sätt alltså beboeligheten
av din organiska
och biologiska kropp.
Sen talar vi om psykosocial beboelighet,
där vi behöver leva med andra invånare, män och kvinnor,
och igen, detta är inte en enkel sak att göra.
Till sist finns en slutlig tolkning av beboelighet som jag ibland kallar spirituell eller kulturell,
vilket innebär: att verkligen bebo som en mänsklig varelse och inte som ett djur
och därför finns den mänskliga varelsens förmåga att skapa en kulturell värld
som är behaglig att leva i, att växa och frodas i,
och det alltså är på denna nivå som vi tolkar beboelighet.
Jag heter Laura Pandelle och jag arbetar som designer för en sammanslutning som heter *La 27e région*
och vi definierar oss själva som ett laboratorium för aktionsforskning om fransk offentlig politik.
Med offentlig politik menar vi alla artefakter, tjänster och processer som är
införda av den allmänna makten, alltså av stat och lokala myndigheter,
för att stödja medborgarnas liv, som medborgare.
Det här uppdraget grundlades när sammanslutningen skapades
och syftar till att skapa kanaler, att fördjupa oss själva i offentliga faciliteter, t.ex. en skola, en tågstation, ett sjukhus
och vi lever där.
Vårt team består av socioliger, arkitekter, designer och ibland konstnärer.
Vi bor på platsen och försöker förstå vad som inte fungerar med en viss offentlig facilitet,
vad problemet är.
Finns det situationer när människor blir aggresiva eller våldsamma,
finns det stressade människor eller klagomål,
finns det spänningar mellan anställda, brist på förståelse, brist på skyltning?
Vi behöver leva där, möta människor, tillbringa tid med dem och ställa frågor till alla lokala intressenter
och sedan, när vi med stöd i erfarenheten har ställt en diagnos,
och genom att ta tillvara användarnas expertis snarare än beslutsfattarnas,
kan vi agera, föreslå och testa lösningar medan vi fortfarande är kvar på plats.
Det här bordet startade med en detalj
Jag hittade en lite metalldel
på mina farföräldrars gård
och den metalldelen var vriden
för att ge mer stabilitet till en specifik funktion.
I normala fall har du metall,
en meltallbit som bara är rak sådär,
den ger ingen stabilitet i den här riktningen
eftersom den är som papper, ett pappersark som är sådär
men mycket stabilitet i den här riktningen,
och om du vrider den,
så ger den tredimentionaltiet, den blir mer stabil.
*Works that Work* är en tidskrift,
min bakgrund är design och jag noterade att inte läste många designtidskrifter,
av olika skäl.
Jag tror att det främsta skälet är att de ofta stannar i en bubbla,
de är skrivna av designers, för designers
och de utesluter en större publik.
Det går att se att de mest specialiserade tidskrifterna blir de mest elitistiska
eller exkluderar en annan läsekrets
och designers tror att deras arbete är relevan för en bredare publik.
Designers tror att deras arbete kan förändra världen,
de tror att deras arbete är giltigt för alla samhällsnivåer och olika samhällsklasser
men i praktiken förblir diskussioner om design mycket isolerade.
Så jag vill se om det fanns en möjlighet att skapa en publikation som handlade om design, men inte för designers
som handlade om förtjänsterna,
som handlade om syftet, som handlade mer om
idéer än om utseende.
Jag måste säga att tidskriften för mig har lyckats eftersom min bror läser den och tycker att den är relevant,
han tycker att
den inte innehåller jargong, den handlar inte om hur saker ser ut
utan den handlar om enkla, grundläggande saker:
how you can improve a quality of life on differents places,
hur en kan förbättra livskvalitet på olika platser,
det är mycket praktiska saker, som hur en kan lösa trafiksituationer utan att
tillföra trafikskyltar,
verkligt grundläggande saker som hur
globaliseringen kunde ske genom en enkel
förbättring av logistik.
När vi startade *Works that Work*
var det tydlgit att vi ville hitta den mest direkta vägen till läsarna
att skära bort allt som låg imellan
och även att tidskriften verkligen finansieras av läsare, inte av någon annan,
det finns inga externa finansieringskällor.
*Works that Work* vill undersöka designområden som ofta ignoreras.
I detta syftes anda försöker vi också kringgå traditionella distributionsnätverk
som vanligtvis tar den största andelen av lösnummerpriset,
och dessutom kontrollerar var publikationen kommer att sälja och till vilket pris.
Vi vill istället fördjupa relationen till våra läsare
och göra dem till partners i detta företag, vi kallar detta *social distribution*.
Därför har vi så kallade bokklubbar där människor helt enkelt får en bunt tidskrifter,
till sina vänner,
och i gengäld kan vi ge dem tidskriften för det pris som distributören normal betalar,
så de får den för halva priset.
så det är en win-win situation.
Vi skapade den mest direkta kopplingen med läsaren
och de belönades eftersom vi kringgår hela distributionskedjan.
Designers arbete handlar inte bara om att skapa ett nytt objekt eller en ny produkt eller en ny tjänst,
det är att tänka om detta objekt i kontexten av människors liv
med konsekvenser, med problem, med begränsningar, med möjligheter, med nackdelar
och ju mer en designer föregriper dessa saker
desto bättre blir det eftersom de då skulle
justera eller anpassa sina projekt.
*Refugeye* är ett projekt som jag utvecklat internt
det är ett mycket enkelt projekt, det är en app
som fungerar i en smartphone och som möjliggör förenklad kommunikation mellan flyktingar
medborgare och organisationer, välgörenhetsorganiationer etc. genom piktogram.
Gränssnittet är mycket enkelt, det är ett gränssnitt där det finns en grupp av piktogram, eller symboler,
jag kan söka på många olika språk, på farsi, engelska,
cyrillic and russian, you name it.
Sen kan jag dra piktogrammet jag valt till min telefon och sen visa det stort,
Jag kan numrera dem i prioritetsordning, jag kan ringa in dem, korsa över dem, skriva över dem.
Och på så vis, utan ord,
kan jag förklara begrepp som kan vara svåra eller känsliga, om censur, att fly från sitt land,
sexualitet, tortyr etc.
så många begrepp som kan vara svåra och komplexa att diskutera.
Jag finansierade det själv, jag skapade det från insikter, användartester etc.
så jag följde verkligen en specifik process
och sen överförde jag allt till en plattform för öppen källkod, jag gjorde projektet så fritt som jag kunde
och det används av flyktingar idag,
jag tror de använder det på *SOS Mediterranee*
och *Bibliothèques sans Frontières* har också installerat appen tillsammans med sina andra verktyg.
Så det är så jag arbetar, jag utvecklar och sprider någonting,
oavsett om det väcker intresse eller inte, jag bara testar saker
och om det inte väcker intresse finns det tusen andra projekt att utveckla.
Så det är den sortens saker jag alltmer försöker utveckla.
Jag tror att jag har varit något av en ensamvarg hela min karriär,
jag har alltid, antingen det handlar om arkitektur, inte tyckt om
eller trott någon ekonomisk modell mot vilken vi byggt
oavsett om det varit kommersiella projekt som givits till mig i industridesign och
arbetat runt dessa instruktioner.
Jag tror att jag alltid har
motiverats av bristen på någonting i världen
som jag känt jag borde, du vet, behovet av
privatliv och säkerhet är problem, eller har varit och kommer alltid att vara viktiga.
Men vi är vid en tidpunkt när vi har fler och fler
enheter, produkter och tjänster uppkopplade till internet,
fler organisationer anslutna till webben också
och mer personlig data blir producerad än insamlad
och just nu är vi i ett läge där,
vi som användare har liten eller ingen kontroll på något av det där.
Det finns en möjlighet tror jag
för design att komma in och återbalansera en del av det där,
att börja tänka på hur vi kan designa tjänster som stärker människor.
Så jag har startat *IF*
egentligen av frustration över att integritet och säkerhet inte uppmärsammades
på ett meningsfullt sätt
i organisationer för några år sedan,
nu menar jag att landskapet har förändrats i stor utsträckning,
jag tror att det politiska landskapet har flyttat fram en det av det där,
men mer och mer när jag talar med människor om vad jag gör
istället för att säga:
“varför gör du detta”, “varför är det intressant”,
säger de: “det där är så viktigt, jag är så glad att hitta någon som faktisk tittar på detta".
Integritet och privatliv är en av frihetes grundvalar,
utan tvivel kommer den digitala eran
i kommunikationsteknologi att höja oron
över känsligheten i personlig information
som kan bli insamlad och blottad om individuella medborgare
och den ständigt ökande genomslagskraften
av sådan datainsamling.
I vilket yrke som helst kan du finna människor som går för långt,
jag talar om aggresiv medecinsk terapi
det är en yrkesmässig handling som går för långt,
finns det motsvarande överskridande inom design?
Naturligtvis finns det det, designers är inte mer perfekta än andra,
eftersom de utsätts för samma lockelser.
Den främsta är konstnärens lockelse,
konstnärens lockelse att vara arrogant,
lockelsen att signera med sitt namn,
lockelsen att vara på en tidskrifts glansiga omslag,
lockelsen att vara en kändis, varken mer eller mindre.
Denna uppfattning,
att stora designers kan vara kändisar
för att de har tillfört världen mer skit,
ja, *Design* är för mig en mycket problematisk industri.
Vilken annan industri gör kändisar av människor
som designar saker som bara ett fåtal har råd med?
Designer som en upphovsman
vilkens
perspektiv bara är fantastiskt och skulle
göra sina verk utifrån sin geniala kreativitet.
Det finns många myter om designers kreativiet som
lämnar de designers som är intresserade av människor, av fältarbete, på ett sätt
delvis utanför bilden.
Det är inte nödvändigtvis sant för alla designers men
jag tror att det finns en tendens
att många kommersiella designers inte är intresserade av
riktiga människor utan mer av sina perspektiv och myter om människor.
Avseende risker med design,
tror jag det är
designen möljliggörande.
Sakerna som kan påverka design är design som påverkas av marknadsföring
eller av andra typer av krafter.
Lite som när du talar om green-washing,
jag är vaksam mot design som skulle kunna användas som human-washing,
där plötsligt alla företag, även de värsta, blir etiska, sociala, politiskt engagerade, altruistiska etc.
Och om design är i maskopi med en sån typ av kidnappning
så tror jag att design blir ett vapen för att manipulera andra.
Oj, jag tror att design har en mängd utmaningar
eftersom många organisationer, de inser inte ens att design borde vara en fråga vid dessa möten, eller hur?
Så du talar inte bara om etik, du talar också om att design borde vara här,
vi har legitima skäl att vara
med i det här samtalet, som den del av det här beslutet.
Så på många ställen är vi inte
bedömda som viktiga i dessa företag.
Med det sagt,
när du tar upp etik i samtalet
tror jag att de utmaningar som designers står inför är
att teknologin har rört sig otroligt snabbt,
om du inte har hängt med hittills,
så behöver du börja titta på det omedelbart
för du har en massa att lära dig
och jag tror inte det är menat att låta skrämmande eller hotfullt,
om detta betyder något för dig så måste du avsätta lite tid till det och du behöver
börja prata med människor som förstår:
backend system, hur det fungerar,
börja prata med ekonomer om informationsekonomin,
forma några åsikter, forma i alla fall några användbara åsikter i alla fall
om de här sakerna.
S jag menar att det finns utmaningar
den här världen har rört sig och förändrat sig mycket snabbt
och om du inte hänger med blir det en stor klyfta att hoppa över.
Jag tror att det enda sättet på vilket vi kan praktisera ansvarsfull design
är genom att förstå komplexiteten i den värld som vi rör oss i.
Problemet med design för närvarande är att den reducerar denna komplexitet,
den simplifierar och gör det banalt,
eftersom den har det här mycket, mycket enkla målet att skapa bra produkter.
Att definiera *bra* är problemet,
att designa bättre är problemet,
och jag tror att detta är problemet med design,
den har en mycket naiv syn på vad som är bra och vad som är önskvärt.
Vi använder dess två ord ofta men förstår vi verkligen vad de betyder?
Moral fokuserar på absolut rätt och fel.
det definierar vad som är förbjudet, vad som uppmuntras eller är tillåtet.
Naturligtvis beror detta på tidsepoken och social kontext,
till exempel, kristen moral var inte densamma på 1000-talet eller 1900-talet
och varierade mellan Europas länder.
Etik är den fundamentala tanken bakom vad det innebär att agera bra
för dig själv och andra.
Det betyder att etik inte säger något om vad som är rätt eller fel,
snarare visar den på vägen du ska går för att leva bättre.
Det finns tre centrala teorier som förklarar en “etisk” handling:
Dygdetik, som säger att om en har dygdiga egenskaper som ärlighet, visdom eller mod,
så har en goda intentioner och kommer att agera på ett “etiskt” sätt.
Deontologisk etik fokuserar på det uppträdande som bör följas för att en handling ska vara “etisk”,
oberoende av dess konsekvenser.
Till exempel, medicinsk deotologi förpliktar en läkare att behandla alla patienter
vilka de än må vara.
Consequentialism determines whether an act is “ethical” by evaluating its consequences.
It judges actions based on their observable results
rather than on the intention of the actor
which would be more difficult to know or to prove.
It is sometimes difficult to distinguish ethics from morality
as the two are intrinsically linked.
We can say that ethics tends to be universal
but is constantly reinterpreting what is the best way to live
for you and others.
Morality defines a group of rules and norms
which are only relevant to an individual or social group at a given moment.
First and foremost I think of Ethics as a process,
I think it’s a process by which we
we sort come to understand the way the world ought to be.
So I think science tells us this is the way things are in the world,
I think Ethics tells us this is the way things ought to be.
And so I think it has a lot of resonances with design,
but I think design tells us what we can do even what we want to do
but it doesn’t tell us what we must do and I think this is the unique
purview of Ethics.
On the question of ‘good’, we know that a computer programme is a good one,
because a good programme is a programme
that correctly executes its code,
doesn’t bug,
works smoothly.
However if we had to define a ‘good’ programme from an ethical perspective
what would it be?
What would be the criteria for this
and how would we evaluate those criteria?
Would a good programme,
a good software, a good app
help increase the well-being of humans?
And what would the criteria for this well-being, in which cases?
What would be the criteria from a technical perspective
to increase
well-being, open-mindedness, creativity, user’s autonomy?
So my first question was “can Ethics be computable?”
and at some point it was more.. so I did a project about autonomous vehicles
where I was trying to find,
I was confronting different vehicles to the trolley dilemma,
some kind of trolley dilemma.
So if the car is confronted to a car crash
there’s not  really a proper solution to it.
Let’s say you have to choose between 3 people or 2 people,
so which Ethics you have to apply to them?
And here it was more a design question
because you have to ask what kind of ethics you are going to implement in this car
and who is going to decide for which ethics should be inside this car,
knowing that this car will work for
a lot of different people with different cultures and so on.
And after even the problem was more complicated, let’s say if it’s this car
is manufactured, let’s say by BMW,
as a car with ethics that work well in Germany
but BMW exports a lot of their cars, let’s say in China
so all the ethics will adapt to a context like China.
So this was for autonomous vehicles but
if we look at products as a whole it was more like
how something as subjective as ethics can be
implemented into a generally manufactured good
and how it can adapt to different contexts.
Eventually I think that in all these tendencies related to design
there is something that’s very potent
and that’s the need that leads companies to that stage.
The role of the designer is to follow or influence this tendency,
certainly not to be submitted to it.
So each time we have been led down a particular path
we have always tried, not to change path and create a rupture,
but to say ok, you think that’s the need
but if we push things this way, are you ready to go there or not.
What I find amazing is that
over the last 3-4 years the profession has changed completely,
our teams have changed completely
because if you want to do good design in an organisation whatever its sector or its size,
I think you need to have
this ability to deal with services, UX, architecture, training,
to work with the cultural side of companies, the economic side of cultural institutions
and to be a lot more global.
It’s a huge opportunity because we find ourselves at certain levels
of responsibility on projects that are exactly what we were looking for.
If you look historically at the role of design,
design is a service-based discipline
and that’s why designers do where the money is coming from,
if someone hires them to do whatever they’ll do it.
And very often it’s to stimulate business,
it’s to stimulate economy,
and lot of ideas like designers can potentially have
they can bring social change but in practice
they’re hired to sell more stuff,
to increase consumerism.
Most of designers who work on new products,
they’re not bringing something new but they try to increase sales of something new,
they’re bringing, you know, psychological obsolescence of objects is built into objects.
The reason why we need
new cars, new shoes, new clothes to make you feel like the old one is inadequate
which is often not the case,
like you don’t really need to replace everything all the time.
The idea that technology improves our lives,
I’ve mentioned this point a little while ago but,
design is really at the heart of that.
So if I work for a company and I’m developing a new product,
that product will be better than the previous version
and the lifestyle that I will have as a result of owning this product will be
a more pleasurable lifestyle than the one I would have if I didn’t own this product.
So it becomes impossible for anybody developing a new product
to say this product is gonna be great but it could go wrong in these ways.
When I was working at Google in the US
I had this realisation that
there is more technology in my life than ever before
but for some reasons that felt harder to do all the things I wanted to do with myself.
I felt like there was something fundamentally off in that situation
because if technology is for anything
it seems like it’s for helping us live better, do the things you want to do better
achieve our goals, live by our values.
I’m thinking of Bruno Latour, who was describing
several ways in which technical objects prescribe our behaviour.
You have the objects that force you, that will force you to act as do the underground turnstiles,
you have the objects that will persuade us to act like speed cameras on roads
and the objects that will seduce us or influence our behaviour without any rational reason.
For instance a road that is straight for kilometers on end will incite us to drive faster,
this is not a rational influence on our behaviour.
You can see now I’ve no hands on the wheel,
so it does not require a constant nag or anything like that.
Like if you go to a secondary school right now,
everyone out of lessons is like this,
and scrolling,
and the endorphins people experience from
the rush of likes they get for a selfie.
I mean I’m being really critical and also I’m broadbrush about it
but someone designed that
and someone designed the experience that they’re going through,
someone designed the likes.
And they have been in board meetings, and presentations and user research sessions,
understanding the effect that has on people
but yet that the kind of design work we’re pushing out right now.
In the political situation
in the political situation we find ourselves in right now,
I think it would be wrong for designers to continue,
designing experiences for digital solipsism,
this idea that we are alone in the world with our piece of technology and we have no impact.
For instance
in infinite newsfeed like on twitter or facebook,
what the psychological mechanism there is the same that is used with slot machines.
It’s a kind of randomising of the reward,
because if you think about an infinite feed it’s just a constant never ending stream of rewards to be had,
informational rewards
and when you scroll down, pull down the refresh, you’re sort of pulling the lever on a slot machine.
Basically by sort of privileging our impulses over our intentions,
things like infinite feeds,
they select for us a certain set of impulsive reactions
and I think in politics outrage is a huge one.
But of course they are others that are eventually positive like I think the feeling of awe
or cuteness, or cute kitty photos,
but I think it’s not the question will we be outraged or will we be
having experiences of awe.
It’s more about like will those be moving us towards what you want to be moved towards.
Will they, as Aldous Huxley put it, helping us be irrational in a reasonable way.
Is the system fundamentally on our side is the question ultimately.
Actually right now I’m working on projects that are totally
against my own ethical,
what I studied before.
One of the recent projects I had to work on was a robot delivering pizza,
in Pizza Hut+ in Shanghai.
You develop this robot or you participate in its development,
you know it will affect a lot of people,
a lot of people in China cannot afford to have good studies
and they rely on
to feed their families, on small jobs such as waiter.
And you know that this robot,
when it will go on the market it will make people lose a lot of jobs
but then if I don't do it myself I don't get a salary.
And that’s why it’s an important thing about ethics,
a lot of designers speak about ethics,
sure maybe they have some kind of ethical belief and so on but
how far are you going to sacrifice yourself to really apply your own ethical belief,
and that’s I think a big issue in the design field.
Perhaps the canonical example here is the bench
that is supposed to prevent people living on the streets to sleep on.
When I did this project about designers and ethnography
I interviewed a designer working for the public transport company in Paris
and he told that “yeah I had to design that bench,
I was asked to design on which people could not sleep
so they wouldn't be bums on the bench”
ok that’s kind of tricky in terms of your ethics,
what do you think about that?
“So yeah well I had two options either
I did it or I was just fired”.
That’s the kind of boundary of extreme limit
in which where do designers sit,
can they exert their strategic perspective
or are they just not allowed to do much more than
saying yes ok I’m gonna do this bench.
It’s a hard choice, again like it’s easier for me now,
of course in the beginning it’s more difficult because you’re more dependent,
we have enough work now so I can be more selective.
In the beginning I was lucky that
we’re coming from cultural sector where there is less difficult choices,
now over time I can make these choices now after 15 or 17 years of working
because you built a position to be this place.
I think every choice you make kind of come back to you sooner or later,
if you engage with some kind of strange product
it will come back to you as well, you’ll get more of it, the simple principle here that,
whatever you do you get more of it.
So if you start something you don’t agree with it
you’ll probably get more of the same questions to do it again and again
and people become experts in doing this kind of things.
Then there is also the whole process
of taking a step back and of being able to say no
or to reformulate commissions that we judge non ethical
or contradictory, or not helpful to citizens.
And when that’s the case I’d say each designer will know
where they position themselves between their economic survival
and their desire to… or rather their professional activism,
and whether they will focus more on the commissioner or on the user.
Design so often happens in this vaccuum,
where we spend all of our time thinking about form,
materiality, of fonction, of how we interact with a thing
but always almost in this bubble.
We think about very really rarely what’s outside of this bubble
about the real lives, about the real systems in which people live
and as a consequence this is where problems lie.
Because we have to think about the world in which our products exist
and there is as much complexity that we can possibly cope with
because they’re incredibly complicated.
And I came across this very recently this exact problem
in a conversation with
probably one of the most talented designers I know, product designer,
he’s been practicing for a small company in London
since we graduated from the RCA, we were in the same year.
He’s just taken a job at Amazon as a kind of higher product designer
and I was just talking with him about this idea of ethics and responsibility
because I’m slightly
concerned about some of the things Amazon is currently doing.
Alexa,
would you lie to me?
I always try to tell the truth,
I’m not always right but I will never intentionally lie to you or anyone else
For him he was shocked that I could be questioning
the value of what he's doing.
He thinks he’s contributing amazing things to the world
but he’s thinking on his scale,
he’s thinking about the beautiful products that he makes
and this is the danger within design.
If you rethink things from the bottom
then you could completely do something different
and the magazine is at the,
the financing, the distribution, the production, everything
it felt like ok if we’re doing a new magazine,
we don't have to inherit any existing old platforms or plans,
we can just do it from scratch.
I find it’s very important
to make designers understand the value of the humanities and social sciences
by showing for instance that if you look at history
of technologies for instance, of this sort of products
it can show you that things have been different in the past.
So by using this understanding what have been different in the past
it’s a way to make designers aware that things should be different in the future
and that you can maybe adapt more ethical choices.
So that’s for history,
Anthropology, it shows that in different cultures,
in different places, in different territories in the world,
there are different ways to live and by showing that
that’s also a way to question a design brief, question product, question existing services.
So I take this kind of example of history:
how things have been different in the past,
anthropology: how things are different elsewhere,
as a way, well, as a sort of metaphor
to think about how design education should
open mindset and not necessarily make designers
answer to the client question in a way
it would be a sort of status quo.
We need to have like an open mind if you want
to live in a more habitable near-future world.
We do need I believe
more organizations to start talking about and opening up
some of the patterns that they are exploring and creating,
because we’ve got a window of opportunity right now to come up with some ethical patterns
whether that be about privacy or security or transparency
for people, for generations to come to copy.
Like if you think about a payment window for credit card on an online service
and if i ask you right now to design me a credit card service
you’ll picture the one you used last week and kind of copy that.
Designers are really good at copying each other
but when it comes to ethics I don’t think we’ve got any blueprints to copy.
So I think we have a window of opportunity, a very exciting opportunity,
to make some of these patterns and guidelines for people to follow
so I think that’s a really big challenge because without these patterns,
it’s more expensive, it’s more time-consuming
to bring ethics into your work
and that doesn't mean you shouldn't do it
but it’s just that the barriers are there
and there’s more obstacles to get past.
And I think that the more difficult the context
the more resistant to a critical approach to design
the more interesting it is.
Because if you manage to influence a large company
which is very difficult to negotiate,
if you manage to influence them 1% or 2% in the first year,
in five years time you’ve done that much,
that’s huge, and you feel that with a little bit of influence
you can do a lot to a big outfit so find this interesting.
So what happens if design starts to happen locally
the way we’re talking about consuming energy locally.
So this is the principle in the gravity battery, the energy being something local,
being through the wall, so you can see the energy that you’re consuming
but also to design a product that can be done locally.
So local manufacturers, local skills,
using local crafts people perhaps,
it’s very much the whole idea of open source hardware
of sharing knowledge,
a lot of the maker labs or maker spaces are talking about this stuff.
you know I think there’s a number of things designers can do,
one of the first thing is kind of just awareness
that there is a problem.
There’s is a lot of optimism in the tech industry,
a lot of it is well justified,
but a lot of it is I think
not as sensitive to
what in economic terms you can called externalities of the design.
So things like distraction would be one of these things
whether that’s a minor annoyance or
a habit that you develop over time that keeps you from being able to reach your goals.
The reason designers don't really see this it’s we don't measure them,
it’s kind of like pollution was in the environmental mouvement.
We knew that stuff was getting dumped into rivers,
we knew there was some kind of harm to the environment
but it wasn't until we started measuring it and quantifying it
then we could actually talk about it and hold
the people doing the polluting to account.
And I think it’s a similar situation here
where we kind have a vague notion that there is something wrong
in a deep way with distraction
and the way in which we get habituated into
being how we don't want to be.
But I think we’re still at the very beginning
of figuring out how to talk about that and measure it,
but I think once we do
I think the goal ought to be doing for
our mental environment what we did for the physical environment
with the environmental movement.
So I think that involves then
new responsibilities on the part of companies and designers
to not just measure the value that they’re getting
but the value they’re giving to people but then also
the potential harms or negative effect that the design is causing.
At first sight
there doesn't seem to be much relationship between farming and industry,
but industry produces pollution,
and pollution affects crops,
so a change in industry affects farming by pollution.
The man-made world consists of a whole complex of subtle relationships like that
change one thing
and it sets up a slow and complicated chain reaction.
Understanding is really, is in a way the key,
like if you understand things,
you respect things,
and if you respect things then,
you take care about things
and then everything's not fine
but better.
Virtuous ethics revolve around the qualities
that a good designer
should integrate
should control or
should apply
in order to do a good job,
except of course the virtue of professional competence and mastering design practice,
these are important
but not sufficient.
I have difficulty framing recommendations for others,
again it’s the same with any piece of advice,
I think the best piece of advice is like to be sceptical of other people’s advice
because I think nowadays there’s too much information available everywhere
and everyone is providing clear-cut answers
like how to do things, there’s books on how to do that how to do this.
You can see ten tips to improve whatever,
from your sex life to your design skills to whatever,
I think people should stop paying attention to these things
and start paying attention to themselves.
So I think developing sceptical attitude
towards other people’s advice because it’s not relevant
is a key.
The main quality, which has been there since the beginning
and  stayed throughout all the various steps Sismo has been undergoing is dialogue.
And even more tomorrow
with all these tools for everyone which keep isolating us,
the role of the designer is to create dialogue, that’s the only thing that works.
The more people the more we need to talk,
to hear each other, to learn to argue with each other
and the role of a project is sometimes to simply create a dialogue.
It’s not the result,
it’s what type of dialogue I managed to create
around this project
and I think that the value of dialogue is rising compared to the value of production.
We went from
the value of design, i.e. the number of parts you will be selling at the end,
I think that tomorrow the value of design will be
how important was the dialogue you managed to create,
between how many stakeholders,
with which social and cultural differences,
on what proportion of land.
I would say inquisitiveness, first,
remembering that we are
an experimental subject
which might have disappeared in a few decades
and therefore you must really enjoy yourself,
test ideas and be bold enough
to mix methodologies and approaches.
That’s it, professional inquisitiveness
and the ability to work with non-designers,
it’s a very important
virtue.
I think honesty,
now I feel I’m not.
For example I’m working on projects that are against my own ethics,
so I don't want to go to designer conferences to speak about my research
because I don't feel it
it was right to speak about it at the time I was doing it
but now I don't feel it’s right to speak about it
when I’m actually doing the opposite of
what I believe.
On the blog we’ve got
it’s almost a manifesto but Philippe Starck features in one of our challenges,
it’s to get rid of vacuous design bullshit.
So Philippe Starck talks about the juicy salif lemon squeezer as,
this juicy salif lemon squeezer is meant to,
it’s not to squeeze lemon, it’s to start conversations.
This is the line.
It’s a lemon squeezer I don't know what kind of conversations he’s expecting or hoping
to start with that particular object.
So I don't know if this is the most important virtue
but it’s one that is really important to me right now.
I think designers who are interested in ethics
and who are
wanting to better their practice,
the virtue you should have or you could learn is to be open.
I think we have so much to thank open source communities
that have built so many of the infrastructures we rely on
but also,
really right now,
to bring ethics into digital products
which is my world of ethics, it’s really digital,
there is so much work to be done
if we
do brilliant work and make it closed,
it will have
a limited effect on any design we see around us.
I mean I suppose one of the most important virtues for a designer
to cultivate will be care,
care for the user.
Because you know you can be the best designer in the world technically
but if you don't care about the person you’re designing it for,
their life and their success,
your really effective design
might be effective in the wrong direction, it could make their life worse.
I think of ethics,
a lot of people thinks of ethics as a brake pedal on innovation,
they say it’s just another box to tick on a document,
it’s an other committee,
but I think of it less as a brake pedal and more as a steering wheel
and if not an accelerator even sometimes.
You know it’s like a tree I just try to grow
and as more as I grow,
the more space I take but not for nothing,
I take more space also to cover other things.
It’s pretty much like
in nature in the end
technical direction and developmentSylvain Juléart direction and graphic designClément Le Tulle-Neyret
direction, production and animationGauthier RoussilhetranslationElise Leclerc
audio post-production and mixMiroslav PilonvoiceoverVictoria Stephensmusic curationSébastien Robert
musicS.A.M. - *Baby I'm Sorry, Alone In A Crowd, Two Hearts In Doubt* - DJ Sports - *Phases Of Winds, The Secret Jog Life* - Trux - *Aziol*
Thank you for your time.