Ik hield echt van het maken van dingen
maar het werd steeds vermoeiender om andermans ideeën te maken
en ik werd erg cynisch over de reclamewereld.
Veel werk dat we deden bestond uit
het maken van tv-reclames
om producten te verkopen die ik niet erg kon waarderen.
Dus toen ik 29 was heb ik me aangemeld bij
de Royal College of Art
om een opleiding genaamd Design Products te volgen.
Ron Arad, de architect en ontwerper, had net
de leerstoel van die opleiding overgenomen.
Er werd me een plek aangeboden en ik begon er
en daardoor maakte ik kennis met,
ik denk, het soort werk dat we nu nog steeds doen:
design met een kritische inslag,
design gebruiken om technologie in vraag te stellen,
heel veel interessante producten maken die
dat doen in plaats van teksten te schrijven,
objecten en ontworpen voorwerpen gebruiken die
de manier, waarop we over dingen nadenken, veranderen,
doe het aanmoedigen om anders na te denken over
technologie en technologische producten.
Je hebt een apparaat waar het signaal binnenkomt
maar dat zendt dan
een lage frequentie in de mond
en dat wordt dan vertaald
naar een trilling
in het binnenoor en dat wordt waargenomen als
geluid, een stroom van geluid.
De mogelijkheden zijn eindeloos,
eerste ministers kunnen geheime aanwijzingen krijgen van hun speciaal adviseurs,
voetbal coaches kunnen tactische informatie overbrengen aan hun spelers
en niemand zal het ooit weten.
Stel je de kerel voor op de effectenbeurs,
of hij nu naar het theater is, naar de bioscoop, of hij in bed of op het strand ligt,
effectengeruchten, informatie over omvallende bedrijven enzovoort
zouden hem meteen kunnen bereiken en hij kan erop reageren.
Ik begon te denken aan Mo's energie-onafhankelijkheidsproject
en ik begon te kijken naar het landschap van Madeira.
Je kan het niet zo goed zien door waar de camera nu op gericht is
maar de richting waar ik nu in kijk, zie ik die gigantische kliffen,
Madeira heeft een extreem verticaal landschap.
Dus ik begon me af te vragen wat Mo's project zou kunnen zijn op Madeira
en al heel gauw kwam ik met dit idee van een zwaartekracht-batterij.
Dus in een notendop, de zwaartekracht-batterij,
dat is een apparaat dat werkt als een opslag
dus je gebruikt nog steeds je zonnepanelen of windmolens,
of wat voor hernieuwbare energie-opwekkende techniek dan ook, maar die energie
wordt opgewekt als de zon schijnt, vaak wanneer de mensen op hun werk zijn of niet thuis zijn,
wanneer ze het vermogen niet nodig hebben.
Op dit moment is de enige oplossing om het terug te verkopen aan het netwerk,
dus aan de eigenaars van de infrastructuur,
en jaar na jaar na jaar hebben ze de prijs die je daarvoor krijgt zitten verlagen, waardoor het onrendabel is geworden.
Met de zwaartekracht-batterij geven we mensen de mogelijkheid om met deze zonne-energie een massa
omhoog te takelen en met zoveel kliffen op Madeira kan dat alles van
tussen de 10-14 meter of helemaal tot 500 meter hoog zijn.
Dus hoe meer hoogte je hebt, hoe meer tijd je hebt om de massa te laten zakken en hoe meer energie je in wezen kan opslaan.
Dus overdag takel je de massa op en wanneer je dan thuis komt en de energie nodig hebt,
het is donker, er schijnt geen zon meer – dan laat je de massa zakken
via een versnellingsbak die een generator aandraait om electriciteit op te wekken.
Het is allemaal open source,
dus we laten de rol van de grote bedrijven en massale fabrieken achterwege,
we maken het makkelijk om te bouwen, dus de huidige versie gebruikt een motorfiets motor
die we op de sloop vonden, het is heel goedkoop,
dus we hergebruiken de versnellingsbak van de motorfiets
omdat ze heel accuraat zijn en al kant-en-klaar
en dan spelen we gewoon wat met de versnellingen en met de massa,
we spelen wat met de valsnelheid en zo kunnen we het op veel verschillende huishoudelijke apparaten afstemmen.
In Nîmes opperden we de term "bewoonbaarheid" van een wereld.
We zeggen dat design kan proberen
om de "bewoonbaarheid" van de wereld
te behouden of te verhogen voor haar inwoners, mannen en vrouwen.
We interpreteren het werkwoord "bewonen" op verschillende niveaus.
Het eerste niveau is natuurlijk stoffelijk,
wat het bewonen van een ruimte betekent, beschut van weersomstandigheden, etcetera. Ik zal niet op dit niveau blijven hangen.
Dan heb je bewoonbaarheid vanuit een vitaal perspectief,
waarbij je gezond moet blijven,
dus op een bepaalde manier de bewoonbaarheid
van je organische
en biologische lichaam.
Daarna spreken we van psychosociale bewoonbaarheid,
waarbij je moet samenleven met andere bewoners, mannen en vrouwen,
en ook dit is niet altijd eenvoudig.
En tenslotte is er een laatste interpretatie van bewoonbaarheid die ik soms spiritueel of cultureel noem,
wat betekent: echt bewonen als een mens en niet als een dier.
and daarvoor is het de eigenschap van de mens om een culturele wereld te creëren
die aangenaam is om in te leven, in te groeien en in te bloeien,
en dus is het op dat niveau dat we bewoonbaarheid interpreteren.
Mijn naam is Laura Pandelle, ik werk als ontwerper voor een vereniging genaamd La 27e Région
en we omschrijven onszelf als laboratorium voor actieonderzoek naar het Franse overheidsbeleid.
Met overheidsbeleid bedoelen we alle dingen, diensten en alle processen die
ingezet worden door de openbare macht, d.w.z. de staat en regionale authoriteiten,
om het leven van de Franse burgers als burger te vergemakkelijken.
Dit is dus een programma dat we sinds de oprichting van de vereniging hebben
dat zich richt op het waarnemen, het onderdompelen van onszelf in een openbare dienst, wat een school kan zijn, een station, een ziekenhuis
om daar dan te wonen,
dus een klein team bestaande uit sociologen, architecten, ontwerpers en soms beeldend kunstenaars.
We wonen ter plekke en we proberen te begrijpen wat er niet werkt in die openbare dienst
waar het probleem ligt.
Zijn er situaties waarin mensen aggressief of gewelddadig worden in bepaalde omgevingen,
zijn er gestreste mensen of klachten,
zijn er spanningen tussen de ambtenaren, gebrek aan duidelijkheid, of bewegwijzering.
Je moet ter plaatse wonen, de mensen ontmoeten, tijd met hen doorbrengen en vragen stellen aan alle betrokkenen
en dan, eenmaal we de diagnose hebben gedaan door deze ervaringen
en door het ondervragen van de expertise van de gebruikers in plaats van die van de besluitvormers,
dan kunnen we handelen, en oplossingen testen en suggereren terwijl we ter plaatse zijn.
Deze tafel begon met een detail.
Ik vond een klein stukje metaal
in de tuin van mijn grootouders
en dat stukje metaal was gedraaid
om meer stevigheid te geven aan een bepaalde functie.
Dus normaal gezien heb je een metalen,
een metalen stuk dat recht is, zoals dat,
het geeft geen stevigheid in deze richting
want het is zoals papier, een blad papier, zoals dat
maar het geeft veel stevigheid in deze richting,
en als je het draait,
dan krijgt het drie dimensies, het wordt steviger.
*Works that Work* is een magazine,
mijn achtergrond is in design en het viel me op dat ik niet veel design magazines lees,
om verschillende redenen.
De grootste reden is, denk ik, dat ze vaak in een bubbel blijven,
ze zijn geschreven door ontwerpers voor ontwerpers
en ze sluiten een groter publiek buiten.
Je kan echt zien dat het meest gespecialiseerde magazine elitair wordt
of andere doelgroepen buitensluit
en ontwerpers denken dat hun werk relevant is voor een breed publiek.
Ontwerpers denken dat hun werk de wereld kan veranderen,
ze geloven dat hun werk van toepassing is op alle lagen van de samenleving en verschillende manieren van leven
maar in de praktijk blijven discussies in design heel erg geïsoleerd.
Dus ik wilde kijken of er een mogelijkheid was om een publicatie te maken die over ontwerp ging maar niet voor ontwerpers
dat gaat over de deugden,
dat gaat over het doel, dat meer gaat over
ideeën dan over uiterlijke vormen.
Ik moet zeggen dat het magazine in zijn opzet geslaagd is want mijn broer leest het en hij vindt het relevant,
hij vindt dat
er geen vaktaal wordt gebruikt, het gaat niet over hoe dingen eruit zien
maar het gaat over hele simpele dingen:
hoe kun je de levenskwaliteit op verschillende plaatsen verbeteren,
dat zijn hele praktische zaken, zoals hoe men verkeerssituaties kan oplossen zonder
verkeersborden te gebruiken,
echt simpele dingen zoals hoe
globalisatie is ontstaan vanwege simpele
logistieke verbeteringen.
Toen we begonnen met *Works that Work*
was het duidelijk dat we de meest directe lijn naar onze lezers wilden vinden
en alles wat ertussen zat weg te knippen
en daarnaast is het magazine echt gefinancierd door de lezers en niet door iemand anders
er is geen externe bron van financiering.
*Works that Work* wil de vaak genegeerde onderdelen van design onderzoeken.
In de geest daarvan willen we ook de traditionele distributienetwerken omzeilen
die normaal gezien het grootste deel van de prijs pakken.
en ook opleggen waar de publicatie verkocht wordt en aan welke prijs.
In plaats daarvan zouden we graag onze relatie met onze lezers versterken
en ze partners maken in deze onderneming, we noemen dit sociale distributie.
Dus we hebben zogenaamde lezersclubs waar mensen gewoon stapels van het magazine kopen,
voor hun vrienden,
en in ruil kunnen we ze het magazine aanbieden voor de prijs die normaal gezien voor distributeurs is,
dus ze krijgen ze voor de helft van de prijs
dus het is een win-winsituatie.
We hebben de meest directe verbinding met de lezer gemaakt
en zij worden beloond omdat we de hele distributieketen omzeilen.
Ontwerpers houden zich niet alleen bezig met het maken van een nieuw object, een nieuwe product of een nieuwe dienst,
ze denken na over dit object in de context van iemands leven
met de gevolgen, met problemen, met limieten, met kansen en nadelen
en hoe meer ontwerpers op die dingen kunnen anticiperen
hoe beter het zou zijn omdat ze hun projecten
kunnen herbekijken en kunnen aanpassen.
Refugeye is een project dat ik intern ontwikkeld heb
het is een heel simpel project, het is een app
dat op een smartphone werkt en een versimpelde vorm van communicatie mogelijk maakt tussen vluchtelingen
burgers en organisaties, goede doelen etcetera, door pictogrammen.
De interface is heel simpel, het is een interface met een groep pictogrammen, een groep symbolen
Ik kan in heel veel verschillende talen zoeken, in het Perzisch, het Engels,
het Cyrillisch en Russisch, noem maar op.
En dan kan ik de pictogrammen die ik gekozen heb naar mijn telefoon slepen en ze worden groot vertoond,
ik kan ze rangschikken op basis van prioriteit, ik kan ze omcirkelen, ze doorkruisen, eroverheen schrijven.
En op die manier, zonder woorden,
kan ik concepten uitleggen die moeilijk of gevoelig kunnen zijn, over censuur, je land ontvluchten
seksualiteit, marteling etcetera
dus best veel concepten die moeilijk kunnen zijn en complex om te bespreken.
Ik heb het zelf gefinancierd, ik begon met inzichten, gebruikerstests etcetera
dus ik volgde echt een bepaald proces
en toen heb ik alles verhuist naar een open source platform, ik bevrijdde het project zo goed als ik kon
en op dit moment wordt het gebruikt door vluchtelingen,
volgens mij gebruiken ze het op SOS Mediterranee
en Bibliothèques sans Frontières heeft de app ook geïnstalleerd naast hun andere werktuigen.
Dus dat is hoe ik werk, ik ontwikkel en verspreid iets,
en het wordt opgepikt of niet, ik test gewoon dingen uit
en als het niet wordt opgepikt zijn er nog duizend andere projecten om te ontwikkelen.
Dus dat zijn het soort dingen die ik steeds meer probeer te ontwikkelen.
Ik denk dat ik mijn hele carrière een beetje een andersdenkende ben geweest,
ik was altijd — of het nu in architectuur, ik hield niet van
of geloofde niet dat de economische modellen die we hebben gebouwd
of het nu commerciële projecten waren die ik kreeg tijdens industrieel ontwerp en
om die instructies heen te werken.
Ik denk dat ik altijd gemotiveerd
ben geweest door het gebrek aan iets in de wereld
dat ik voelde dat ik zou moeten, je weet wel, de behoefte aan
privacy en veiligheid zijn zaken die nu en vroeger en altijd wel belangrijk zullen zijn.
Maar we leven in een tijd waarin er meer en meer
apparaten, producten en diensten verbonden zijn met het internet,
ook meer organisaties verbonden zijn met het internet,
en er wordt meer persoonlijke data geproduceerd en verzameld
en op dit moment zitten we in een positie waarin,
we als gebruikers niet of nauwelijks controle hebben over dat alles.
Ik denk dat er een opportuniteit is
voor design om hierop in te gaan en het evenwicht een beetje te herstellen,
om na te gaan denken over hoe we diensten kunnen ontwerpen die de controle teruggeeft aan mensen.
Dus ik ben IF begonnen
echt uit frustratie dat men niet omkeek naar privacy en veiligheid
op een betekenisvolle manier
in organisaties een paar jaar geleden,
nu denk ik dat de situatie aanzienlijk veranderd is,
ik denk dat het politieke landschap daar deels voor heeft gezorgd,
maar vaker en vaker als ik met mensen praat over wat ik doe
in plaats van dat ze zeggen:
“waarom zou je dat doen, “waarom is dat interessant”,
zeggen ze “dat is zo belangrijk, ik ben zo blij om iemand te vinden die hier werkelijk mee bezig is".
Privacy is een hoeksteen van vrijheid,
zonder twijfel zal het digitale tijdperk in
communicatietechnologiën in toenemende mate zorgen baren
over de gevoeligheid van persoonlijke informatie
die verzameld of vrijgegeven kan worden over individuele burgers
en de steeds toenemende indringendheid
van zulke dataverzameling.
In elke sector zul je mensen vinden die te ver gaan,
we hebben het over eindeloos doordokteren in de gezondheidszorg,
dat is een professionele daad die te ver gaat,
zijn er soortgelijke buitensporigheden in design?
Natuurlijk zijn die er, ontwerpers zijn net zo min perfects als ieder ander,
en daarom onderworpen aan dezelfde verleidingen.
De belangrijkste is de verleiding van de kunstenaar,
de verleiding van de kunstenaar om arrogant te zijn,
de verleiding om hun werk te ondertekenen,
de verleiding om op de voorkant van een glossy tijdschrift te staan,
de verleiding om een beroemdheid te zijn, zonder meer.
Dit idee
dat uitmuntende ontwerpers beroemdheden kunnen zijn
omdat ze meer rommel de wereld in brengen
ja, design is voor mij een heel problematische sector.
Welke andere sector maakt beroemdheden van mensen
die spullen ontwerpen die maar enkelen zich kunnen veroorloven.
De ontwerper als auteur
wiens
kijk gewoonweg geweldig is en die
hun werk maken vanuit hun geniale creativiteit.
Er zijn allerlei soorten mythes over de creativiteit van ontwerpers
die de ontwerpers die geïnteresseerd zijn in mensen, in veldwerk,
buiten beschouwing laten.
Het geldt niet noodzakelijk voor alle ontwerpers maar
ik denk dat er een tendens heerst
onder veel commerciële ontwerpers om niet geïnteresseerd te zijn in
de werkelijke mensen, maar meer in hun kijk en de mythe over mensen.
Wat betreft de gevaren die aan design gerelateerd zijn,
denk ik dat het
het in staat stellen van design is.
Welnu, de dingen die design kunnen schaden is design in functie van marketing,
design in functie van…
Een beetje zoals wanneer we het hebben over green-washing,
Ik sta wantrouwig tegenover design dat gebruikt zou kunnen worden als human-washing,
waarbij opeens alle bedrijven, zelfs de meest kwaadaardige, ethisch worden, sociaal, politiek betrokken, solidair, etcetera.
En als design samenspant met dit soort kaping
dan denk ik dat design een wapen wordt waarmee je anderen kan manipuleren.
Tsjonge, ik denk dat design veel uitdagingen te overwinnen heeft
want veel organisaties realiseren zich niet eens dat design ook een plaats verdient in die vergaderingen, weet je.
Dus we hebben het hier niet alleen over ethiek, maar over dat design hier ook een plaats verdient,
we hebben een legitieme reden om aanwezig te zijn
in deze conversatie, als deel van deze beslissing.
Dus op veel plekken worden we nog steeds
niet als belangrijk beschouwd in deze bedrijven.
Dat gezegd hebbende,
als je ethiek opbrengt in de conversatie
ik denk dat de uitdaging waar ontwerpers voor staan is dat
technologie onvoorstelbaar snel vooruitgaat,
als je het niet bijgehouden hebt,
dan moet je er nu echt mee beginnen
want je hebt nog veel te leren
en dat is niet bedoeld om eng te klinken of als een dreigement,
als je hier om geeft, dan moet je er wat tijd in investeren en je moet
gaan praten met de mensen die verstand hebben van
backend systemen, hoe dat werkt,
praten met economen over de informatie-economie,
vorm meningen, of in ieder geval nuttige meningen
over die dingen.
Dus ik denk dat de uitdagingen liggen in het feit dat
deze wereld heel snel aan het bewegen en veranderen is
en als je het niet bijhoudt, dan is het een flinke afstand om te overbruggen.
De enige manier waarop we, denk ik, verantwoord design kunnen beoefenen
is door het begrijpen van de complexiteit van de wereld waarin we werken.
Het probleem met design op het moment is dat het complexiteit vermindert,
het versimpelt het en maakt het banaal,
want het heeft dit hele hele simpele doel om goede producten te maken.
Definiëer goed, is het probleem,
ontwerp beter, is het probleem
en ik denk dat dit het probleem is met design,
het heeft een hele naïeve kijk op wat goed en wat wenselijk is.
Ethiek en moraliteit. We gebruiken die twee woorden vaak maar weten we wel echt wat ze betekenen?
Moraliteit focust op het absolute goede en slechte,
het definiëert wat verboden, aangemoedigd of toegelaten is.
Het hangt natuurlijk altijd af van de tijdsgeest en sociale context,
bijvoorbeeld, christelijke moraliteit was niet hetzelfde in de 11e eeuw als in de 20e eeuw
en verschilde tussen Europese landen.
Ethiek is de fundamentele gedachte achter wat het betekent om goed te handelen
voor jezelf en voor anderen.
Dit betekent dat ethiek niet zegt wat goed is en wat slecht,
maar het laat je eerder de manier zien waarop je beter kunt leven.
Er zijn drie hoofdtheoriën die uitleggen wat een ”ethisch” daad is:
Deugdethiek, zegt dat als een mens deugdelijke karakteristieken heeft zoals eerlijkheid, wijsheid of moed,
dan zal hij goede bedoelingen hebben en dus handelen op een ”ethische” manier.
Plichtethiek focust op het gedrag dat gevolgd moet worden om een daad ”ethisch” te laten zijn,
ongeacht de consequenties.
Bijvoorbeeld, medische plichtsethiek verplicht artsen om alle zieke patiënten te behandelen
wie ze ook mogen zijn.
Gevolgenethiek bepaalt of een daad “ethisch” is door de consequenties ervan te beoordelen.
Het beoordeelt daden op hun waarneembare resultaten
in plaats van op de bedoeling van de handelende
wat veel moeilijker te weten of te bewijzen is.
Soms is het moeilijk om ethiek van moraliteit te onderscheiden
omdat de twee onlosmakelijk verbonden zijn.
We kunnen stellen dat ethiek de neiging heeft universeel te zijn
maar voortdurend opnieuw interpreteert wat de beste manier is om te leven
voor jezelf en anderen.
Moraliteit bepaalt een groep regels en normen
die alleen relevant zijn voor een individu of een sociale groep op een gegeven moment in de tijd.
First and foremost I think of Ethics as a process,
I think it’s a process by which we
we sort come to understand the way the world ought to be.
So I think science tells us this is the way things are in the world,
I think Ethics tells us this is the way things ought to be.
And so I think it has a lot of resonances with design,
but I think design tells us what we can do even what we want to do
but it doesn’t tell us what we must do and I think this is the unique
purview of Ethics.
On the question of ‘good’, we know that a computer programme is a good one,
because a good programme is a programme
that correctly executes its code,
doesn’t bug,
works smoothly.
However if we had to define a ‘good’ programme from an ethical perspective
what would it be?
What would be the criteria for this
and how would we evaluate those criteria?
Would a good programme,
a good software, a good app
help increase the well-being of humans?
And what would the criteria for this well-being, in which cases?
What would be the criteria from a technical perspective
to increase
well-being, open-mindedness, creativity, user’s autonomy?
So my first question was “can Ethics be computable?”
and at some point it was more.. so I did a project about autonomous vehicles
where I was trying to find,
I was confronting different vehicles to the trolley dilemma,
some kind of trolley dilemma.
So if the car is confronted to a car crash
there’s not  really a proper solution to it.
Let’s say you have to choose between 3 people or 2 people,
so which Ethics you have to apply to them?
And here it was more a design question
because you have to ask what kind of ethics you are going to implement in this car
and who is going to decide for which ethics should be inside this car,
knowing that this car will work for
a lot of different people with different cultures and so on.
And after even the problem was more complicated, let’s say if it’s this car
is manufactured, let’s say by BMW,
as a car with ethics that work well in Germany
but BMW exports a lot of their cars, let’s say in China
so all the ethics will adapt to a context like China.
So this was for autonomous vehicles but
if we look at products as a whole it was more like
how something as subjective as ethics can be
implemented into a generally manufactured good
and how it can adapt to different contexts.
Eventually I think that in all these tendencies related to design
there is something that’s very potent
and that’s the need that leads companies to that stage.
The role of the designer is to follow or influence this tendency,
certainly not to be submitted to it.
So each time we have been led down a particular path
we have always tried, not to change path and create a rupture,
but to say ok, you think that’s the need
but if we push things this way, are you ready to go there or not.
What I find amazing is that
over the last 3-4 years the profession has changed completely,
our teams have changed completely
because if you want to do good design in an organisation whatever its sector or its size,
I think you need to have
this ability to deal with services, UX, architecture, training,
to work with the cultural side of companies, the economic side of cultural institutions
and to be a lot more global.
It’s a huge opportunity because we find ourselves at certain levels
of responsibility on projects that are exactly what we were looking for.
If you look historically at the role of design,
design is a service-based discipline
and that’s why designers do where the money is coming from,
if someone hires them to do whatever they’ll do it.
And very often it’s to stimulate business,
it’s to stimulate economy,
and lot of ideas like designers can potentially have
they can bring social change but in practice
they’re hired to sell more stuff,
to increase consumerism.
Most of designers who work on new products,
they’re not bringing something new but they try to increase sales of something new,
they’re bringing, you know, psychological obsolescence of objects is built into objects.
The reason why we need
new cars, new shoes, new clothes to make you feel like the old one is inadequate
which is often not the case,
like you don’t really need to replace everything all the time.
The idea that technology improves our lives,
I’ve mentioned this point a little while ago but,
design is really at the heart of that.
So if I work for a company and I’m developing a new product,
that product will be better than the previous version
and the lifestyle that I will have as a result of owning this product will be
a more pleasurable lifestyle than the one I would have if I didn’t own this product.
So it becomes impossible for anybody developing a new product
to say this product is gonna be great but it could go wrong in these ways.
When I was working at Google in the US
I had this realisation that
there is more technology in my life than ever before
but for some reasons that felt harder to do all the things I wanted to do with myself.
I felt like there was something fundamentally off in that situation
because if technology is for anything
it seems like it’s for helping us live better, do the things you want to do better
achieve our goals, live by our values.
I’m thinking of Bruno Latour, who was describing
several ways in which technical objects prescribe our behaviour.
You have the objects that force you, that will force you to act as do the underground turnstiles,
you have the objects that will persuade us to act like speed cameras on roads
and the objects that will seduce us or influence our behaviour without any rational reason.
For instance a road that is straight for kilometers on end will incite us to drive faster,
this is not a rational influence on our behaviour.
You can see now I’ve no hands on the wheel,
so it does not require a constant nag or anything like that.
Like if you go to a secondary school right now,
everyone out of lessons is like this,
and scrolling,
and the endorphins people experience from
the rush of likes they get for a selfie.
I mean I’m being really critical and also I’m broadbrush about it
but someone designed that
and someone designed the experience that they’re going through,
someone designed the likes.
And they have been in board meetings, and presentations and user research sessions,
understanding the effect that has on people
but yet that the kind of design work we’re pushing out right now.
In the political situation
in the political situation we find ourselves in right now,
I think it would be wrong for designers to continue,
designing experiences for digital solipsism,
this idea that we are alone in the world with our piece of technology and we have no impact.
For instance
in infinite newsfeed like on twitter or facebook,
what the psychological mechanism there is the same that is used with slot machines.
It’s a kind of randomising of the reward,
because if you think about an infinite feed it’s just a constant never ending stream of rewards to be had,
informational rewards
and when you scroll down, pull down the refresh, you’re sort of pulling the lever on a slot machine.
Basically by sort of privileging our impulses over our intentions,
things like infinite feeds,
they select for us a certain set of impulsive reactions
and I think in politics outrage is a huge one.
But of course they are others that are eventually positive like I think the feeling of awe
or cuteness, or cute kitty photos,
but I think it’s not the question will we be outraged or will we be
having experiences of awe.
It’s more about like will those be moving us towards what you want to be moved towards.
Will they, as Aldous Huxley put it, helping us be irrational in a reasonable way.
Is the system fundamentally on our side is the question ultimately.
Actually right now I’m working on projects that are totally
against my own ethical,
what I studied before.
One of the recent projects I had to work on was a robot delivering pizza,
in Pizza Hut+ in Shanghai.
You develop this robot or you participate in its development,
you know it will affect a lot of people,
a lot of people in China cannot afford to have good studies
and they rely on
to feed their families, on small jobs such as waiter.
And you know that this robot,
when it will go on the market it will make people lose a lot of jobs
but then if I don't do it myself I don't get a salary.
And that’s why it’s an important thing about ethics,
a lot of designers speak about ethics,
sure maybe they have some kind of ethical belief and so on but
how far are you going to sacrifice yourself to really apply your own ethical belief,
and that’s I think a big issue in the design field.
Perhaps the canonical example here is the bench
that is supposed to prevent people living on the streets to sleep on.
When I did this project about designers and ethnography
I interviewed a designer working for the public transport company in Paris
and he told that “yeah I had to design that bench,
I was asked to design on which people could not sleep
so they wouldn't be bums on the bench”
ok that’s kind of tricky in terms of your ethics,
what do you think about that?
“So yeah well I had two options either
I did it or I was just fired”.
That’s the kind of boundary of extreme limit
in which where do designers sit,
can they exert their strategic perspective
or are they just not allowed to do much more than
saying yes ok I’m gonna do this bench.
It’s a hard choice, again like it’s easier for me now,
of course in the beginning it’s more difficult because you’re more dependent,
we have enough work now so I can be more selective.
In the beginning I was lucky that
we’re coming from cultural sector where there is less difficult choices,
now over time I can make these choices now after 15 or 17 years of working
because you built a position to be this place.
I think every choice you make kind of come back to you sooner or later,
if you engage with some kind of strange product
it will come back to you as well, you’ll get more of it, the simple principle here that,
whatever you do you get more of it.
So if you start something you don’t agree with it
you’ll probably get more of the same questions to do it again and again
and people become experts in doing this kind of things.
Then there is also the whole process
of taking a step back and of being able to say no
or to reformulate commissions that we judge non ethical
or contradictory, or not helpful to citizens.
And when that’s the case I’d say each designer will know
where they position themselves between their economic survival
and their desire to… or rather their professional activism,
and whether they will focus more on the commissioner or on the user.
Design so often happens in this vaccuum,
where we spend all of our time thinking about form,
materiality, of fonction, of how we interact with a thing
but always almost in this bubble.
We think about very really rarely what’s outside of this bubble
about the real lives, about the real systems in which people live
and as a consequence this is where problems lie.
Because we have to think about the world in which our products exist
and there is as much complexity that we can possibly cope with
because they’re incredibly complicated.
And I came across this very recently this exact problem
in a conversation with
probably one of the most talented designers I know, product designer,
he’s been practicing for a small company in London
since we graduated from the RCA, we were in the same year.
He’s just taken a job at Amazon as a kind of higher product designer
and I was just talking with him about this idea of ethics and responsibility
because I’m slightly
concerned about some of the things Amazon is currently doing.
Alexa,
would you lie to me?
I always try to tell the truth,
I’m not always right but I will never intentionally lie to you or anyone else
For him he was shocked that I could be questioning
the value of what he's doing.
He thinks he’s contributing amazing things to the world
but he’s thinking on his scale,
he’s thinking about the beautiful products that he makes
and this is the danger within design.
If you rethink things from the bottom
then you could completely do something different
and the magazine is at the,
the financing, the distribution, the production, everything
it felt like ok if we’re doing a new magazine,
we don't have to inherit any existing old platforms or plans,
we can just do it from scratch.
I find it’s very important
to make designers understand the value of the humanities and social sciences
by showing for instance that if you look at history
of technologies for instance, of this sort of products
it can show you that things have been different in the past.
So by using this understanding what have been different in the past
it’s a way to make designers aware that things should be different in the future
and that you can maybe adapt more ethical choices.
So that’s for history,
Anthropology, it shows that in different cultures,
in different places, in different territories in the world,
there are different ways to live and by showing that
that’s also a way to question a design brief, question product, question existing services.
So I take this kind of example of history:
how things have been different in the past,
anthropology: how things are different elsewhere,
as a way, well, as a sort of metaphor
to think about how design education should
open mindset and not necessarily make designers
answer to the client question in a way
it would be a sort of status quo.
We need to have like an open mind if you want
to live in a more habitable near-future world.
We do need I believe
more organizations to start talking about and opening up
some of the patterns that they are exploring and creating,
because we’ve got a window of opportunity right now to come up with some ethical patterns
whether that be about privacy or security or transparency
for people, for generations to come to copy.
Like if you think about a payment window for credit card on an online service
and if i ask you right now to design me a credit card service
you’ll picture the one you used last week and kind of copy that.
Designers are really good at copying each other
but when it comes to ethics I don’t think we’ve got any blueprints to copy.
So I think we have a window of opportunity, a very exciting opportunity,
to make some of these patterns and guidelines for people to follow
so I think that’s a really big challenge because without these patterns,
it’s more expensive, it’s more time-consuming
to bring ethics into your work
and that doesn't mean you shouldn't do it
but it’s just that the barriers are there
and there’s more obstacles to get past.
And I think that the more difficult the context
the more resistant to a critical approach to design
the more interesting it is.
Because if you manage to influence a large company
which is very difficult to negotiate,
if you manage to influence them 1% or 2% in the first year,
in five years time you’ve done that much,
that’s huge, and you feel that with a little bit of influence
you can do a lot to a big outfit so find this interesting.
So what happens if design starts to happen locally
the way we’re talking about consuming energy locally.
So this is the principle in the gravity battery, the energy being something local,
being through the wall, so you can see the energy that you’re consuming
but also to design a product that can be done locally.
So local manufacturers, local skills,
using local crafts people perhaps,
it’s very much the whole idea of open source hardware
of sharing knowledge,
a lot of the maker labs or maker spaces are talking about this stuff.
you know I think there’s a number of things designers can do,
one of the first thing is kind of just awareness
that there is a problem.
There’s is a lot of optimism in the tech industry,
a lot of it is well justified,
but a lot of it is I think
not as sensitive to
what in economic terms you can called externalities of the design.
So things like distraction would be one of these things
whether that’s a minor annoyance or
a habit that you develop over time that keeps you from being able to reach your goals.
The reason designers don't really see this it’s we don't measure them,
it’s kind of like pollution was in the environmental mouvement.
We knew that stuff was getting dumped into rivers,
we knew there was some kind of harm to the environment
but it wasn't until we started measuring it and quantifying it
then we could actually talk about it and hold
the people doing the polluting to account.
And I think it’s a similar situation here
where we kind have a vague notion that there is something wrong
in a deep way with distraction
and the way in which we get habituated into
being how we don't want to be.
But I think we’re still at the very beginning
of figuring out how to talk about that and measure it,
but I think once we do
I think the goal ought to be doing for
our mental environment what we did for the physical environment
with the environmental movement.
So I think that involves then
new responsibilities on the part of companies and designers
to not just measure the value that they’re getting
but the value they’re giving to people but then also
the potential harms or negative effect that the design is causing.
At first sight
there doesn't seem to be much relationship between farming and industry,
but industry produces pollution,
and pollution affects crops,
so a change in industry affects farming by pollution.
The man-made world consists of a whole complex of subtle relationships like that
change one thing
and it sets up a slow and complicated chain reaction.
Understanding is really, is in a way the key,
like if you understand things,
you respect things,
and if you respect things then,
you take care about things
and then everything's not fine
but better.
Virtuous ethics revolve around the qualities
that a good designer
should integrate
should control or
should apply
in order to do a good job,
except of course the virtue of professional competence and mastering design practice,
these are important
but not sufficient.
I have difficulty framing recommendations for others,
again it’s the same with any piece of advice,
I think the best piece of advice is like to be sceptical of other people’s advice
because I think nowadays there’s too much information available everywhere
and everyone is providing clear-cut answers
like how to do things, there’s books on how to do that how to do this.
You can see ten tips to improve whatever,
from your sex life to your design skills to whatever,
I think people should stop paying attention to these things
and start paying attention to themselves.
So I think developing sceptical attitude
towards other people’s advice because it’s not relevant
is a key.
The main quality, which has been there since the beginning
and  stayed throughout all the various steps Sismo has been undergoing is dialogue.
And even more tomorrow
with all these tools for everyone which keep isolating us,
the role of the designer is to create dialogue, that’s the only thing that works.
The more people the more we need to talk,
to hear each other, to learn to argue with each other
and the role of a project is sometimes to simply create a dialogue.
It’s not the result,
it’s what type of dialogue I managed to create
around this project
and I think that the value of dialogue is rising compared to the value of production.
We went from
the value of design, i.e. the number of parts you will be selling at the end,
I think that tomorrow the value of design will be
how important was the dialogue you managed to create,
between how many stakeholders,
with which social and cultural differences,
on what proportion of land.
I would say inquisitiveness, first,
remembering that we are
an experimental subject
which might have disappeared in a few decades
and therefore you must really enjoy yourself,
test ideas and be bold enough
to mix methodologies and approaches.
That’s it, professional inquisitiveness
and the ability to work with non-designers,
it’s a very important
virtue.
I think honesty,
now I feel I’m not.
For example I’m working on projects that are against my own ethics,
so I don't want to go to designer conferences to speak about my research
because I don't feel it
it was right to speak about it at the time I was doing it
but now I don't feel it’s right to speak about it
when I’m actually doing the opposite of
what I believe.
On the blog we’ve got
it’s almost a manifesto but Philippe Starck features in one of our challenges,
it’s to get rid of vacuous design bullshit.
So Philippe Starck talks about the juicy salif lemon squeezer as,
this juicy salif lemon squeezer is meant to,
it’s not to squeeze lemon, it’s to start conversations.
This is the line.
It’s a lemon squeezer I don't know what kind of conversations he’s expecting or hoping
to start with that particular object.
So I don't know if this is the most important virtue
but it’s one that is really important to me right now.
I think designers who are interested in ethics
and who are
wanting to better their practice,
the virtue you should have or you could learn is to be open.
I think we have so much to thank open source communities
that have built so many of the infrastructures we rely on
but also,
really right now,
to bring ethics into digital products
which is my world of ethics, it’s really digital,
there is so much work to be done
if we
do brilliant work and make it closed,
it will have
a limited effect on any design we see around us.
I mean I suppose one of the most important virtues for a designer
to cultivate will be care,
care for the user.
Because you know you can be the best designer in the world technically
but if you don't care about the person you’re designing it for,
their life and their success,
your really effective design
might be effective in the wrong direction, it could make their life worse.
I think of ethics,
a lot of people thinks of ethics as a brake pedal on innovation,
they say it’s just another box to tick on a document,
it’s an other committee,
but I think of it less as a brake pedal and more as a steering wheel
and if not an accelerator even sometimes.
You know it’s like a tree I just try to grow
and as more as I grow,
the more space I take but not for nothing,
I take more space also to cover other things.
It’s pretty much like
in nature in the end
technical direction and developmentSylvain Juléart direction and graphic designClément Le Tulle-Neyret
direction, production and animationGauthier RoussilhetranslationElise Leclerc
audio post-production and mixMiroslav PilonvoiceoverVictoria Stephensmusic curationSébastien Robert
musicS.A.M. - *Baby I'm Sorry, Alone In A Crowd, Two Hearts In Doubt* - DJ Sports - *Phases Of Winds, The Secret Jog Life* - Trux - *Aziol*
Thank you for your time.